<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Regis Freyd</title>
    <link href="https://regisfreyd.com" />
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://regisfreyd.com/blog/feed.atom" />
    <updated>2020-02-26T12:34:28+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://regisfreyd.com/blog/feed.atom</id>
    <author>
        <name>Regis Freyd</name>
    </author>
                <entry>
    <id>https://regisfreyd.com/blog/single-point-of-contact</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://regisfreyd.com/blog/single-point-of-contact" />
    <title>Have a single point of contact for your side project</title>
    <published>2020-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2020-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Regis Freyd</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">When your side project gains traction, alongside with being flooded by feature requests, you will receive requests to open a Slack community, or a forum, or to have a newsletter, or to use GitHub issues, or to have a dedicated Twitter account. You will......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>When your side project gains traction, alongside with being flooded by feature requests, you will receive requests to open a Slack community, or a forum, or to have a newsletter, or to use GitHub issues, or to have a dedicated Twitter account. You will also be tempted to record every feature request — because, well, it’s tempting.</p>

<p>Don’t.</p>

<p>If you work on a side project, you will fight every minute of your life to find the time to work on it. You probably have a full-time job, a spouse and/or kids, friends and life in general. Finding 1 or 2 hours per day to work on your passion is tough, and precious.</p>

<p>Do you really want to spend this time maintaining a lot of channels to talk to your community? Don’t get me wrong: having a community around your project is essential. However, the cost of having too many official channels is enormous and drains a lot of attention and energy — energy that you will not spend on doing what you loved in the first place: working on the core of your side project. The more communication channels you have, the more people will /steal/ your time by flooding you with requests or support questions. And as you are kind, you will try to please them — but this is endless.</p>

<p>For your side project, keep one official channel of communication. It could be the GitHub issues of your project or your own Twitter account. That’s it. Communicate with your community through that channel. And focus on your product. When you will find more time to dedicate to it (because the project generates revenues for instance), you will be able to offer other forms of communication. This time will come. But for now, stay sane.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
    </feed>
